Guide to the Harry Shaw Perris Papers, 1907-1926
Department of Special Collections
Perris, Harry Shaw
1907-1926
M0782
1 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Includes papers about the Centenary of the Treaty of Ghent, 1814-1914, publications by Harry Shaw Perris and George Herbert Perris, manuscripts by H.S. Perris, and papers and speeches by other writers.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Purchased, 1995.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 1995.
Biography
English author and academic who wrote and lectured on Anglo-American relations, U.S. history, and issues of war and peace in Europe. As secretary of the British Peace Centenary Committee, Perris was one of the British delegates invited to the United States to assist in the organization of the celebration of the One Hundredth Anniversary of Peace Among English-speaking Peoples, 24 December 1814- 24 December 1914. The U.S. National Committee was organized in New York in February, 1910, with the aim of honoring the Treaty of Ghent and celebrating the century of peace between America and the British Empire. Invitations were extended to many other European countries with the purpose of cultivating world-wide good will. It was less a commemmoration of the past than a covenant of a continuation for the future of present amity and good will. The Honorary Chairman was Theodore Roosevelt but the committee had no governmental nor diplomatic functions.
Scope and Content
Includes papers about the Centenary of the Treaty of Ghent, 1814-1914, publications by Harry Shaw Perris and George Herbert Perris, manuscripts by H.S. Perris, and papers and speeches by other writers.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Perris, George Herbert.; The Peace Centenary Committee.; Peace.
Collection Contents
- Series 1. Centenary of the Treaty of Ghent 1814-1914.
  - National Committee for the Celebration of the One Hundredth Anniversary of Peace Among English-Speaking Peoples 1814-1914; Publication of objectives and list of members. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Banquet given by The American Committee for the Celebration of the One Hundredth Anniversary of Peace ... Friday, 9 May, 1913; Hotel Astor, New York. Printed guest list. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Report of International Conference for the Consideration of the Commemmoration May 5-10, 1913. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Centenary of the Treaty of Ghent, Dec.24, 1814 - Dec.24, 1914."The war it ended, and how and why the Treaty was signed." (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Daily Chronicle, Saturday, April 26, 1913. "One Hundred Years of Peace" British] Delegation to America." Newspaper article and photographs. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photograph found with Banquet list. Unidentified group standing by sculpture. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series 2. Publications: Perris, Harry Shaw, and Perris, George Herbert.
  - Perris, H.S. Rifles and Education: A Record and Appeal. (London: Peace Committee of the Society of Friends, 1907). (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Perris, H.S. A Short History of Anglo-American Relations and of the Hundred Years' Peace. (London: British Peace Centenary, 1914). (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Perris, H.S. The War as Viewed by a Liberal Englishman. (New York: The Sulgrave Institution, 1917). Cornell University Lecture, October, 1917. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Perris, G. H. The War Traders: An Exposure. (Westminster: National Peace Council, 1913). (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series 3. Manuscripts: Perris, H.S.
  - A New Short History of the United States to the end of the War of the Revolution, Revised Typed MS. Preface & Chapter 1. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - A New Short History of the United States to the end of the War of the Revolution, Revised Typed MS. Chapter 2. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - A New Short History of the United States to the end of the War of the Revolution, Revised Typed MS. Chapter 3. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - A New Short History of the United States to the end of the War of the Revolution, Revised Typed MS. Chapter 4. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - A New Short History of the United States to the end of the War of the Revolution, Revised Typed MS. Chapter 5. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - A New Short History of the United States to the end of the War of the Revolution, Revised Typed MS. Chapter 6. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - A New Short History of the United States to the end of the War of the Revolution, Revised Typed MS. Chapter 7. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - A New Short History of the United States. Typed MS Copy with corrections. Preface & Chapters 1-2. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - A New Short History of the United States. Typed MS Copy with corrections. Chapter 3. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - A New Short History of the United States. Typed MS Copy with corrections. Chapter 4. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - A New Short History of the United States. Typed MS Copy with corrections. Chapter 5. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - A New Short History of the United States. Typed MS Copy with corrections. Chapter 6. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - A New Short History of the United States. Typed MS Copy with corrections. Chapter 7. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The United States of America, A Short History for British Colleges and Schools. Typed MS Copy. Preface, Chapter 1; incomplete. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The United States of America, A Short History for British Colleges and Schools. Typed MS Copy. Preface, Chapter 1; incomplete. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The United States of America, A Short History for British Colleges and Schools. Typed MS Copy. Chapter 1. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The United States of America, A Short History for British Colleges and Schools. Typed MS Copy. Chapters 2 and 3. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - The United States of America, A Short History for British Colleges and Schools. Typed MS Copy. Chapters 5, 6, and 7. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - The United States of America, A Short History for British Colleges and Schools. Typed MS Copy. Chapter 7; incomplete. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - A Short History of the United States. Autographic MS, Author's Preface and Chapter 1. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - A Short History of the United States. Autographic MS, Chapter 2. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - A Short History of the United States. Autographic MS, Chapter 3. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - A Short History of the United States. Autographic MS, Chapter 4. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - A Short History of the United States. Autographic MS, Chapter 5. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - A Short History of the United States. Autographic MS, Chapter 6. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - A Short History of the United States. Autographic MS, Chapter 7. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Milestones of Anglo-American Friendship and Other Papers in War and Peace. Typed MS. Preface, Introduction and Chapter 1. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Milestones of Anglo-American Friendship and Other Papers in War and Peace. Typed MS. Chapters 2 and 3. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Milestones of Anglo-American Friendship and Other Papers in War and Peace. Typed MS. Chapter 6. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "America and the Comity of Nations." Typed MS. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "A Word of Cheer- Some Thoughts on the Present Crisis." Typed MS [no author but looks like Perris]. (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Series 4. Papers / Speeches by Other Writers.
  - Dixon, A.C. "Two Civilizations in Conflict." (1918). Typed MS Copy. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Parker, Sir Gilbert. Untitled paper on the loyalty between Canada and the USA in the Great War. Typed MS. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Hobson, J.A. "The Naval Disarmament Failure." (1926). Autograph MS. (Box 2, Folder 14)